<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>Disembrangling Programming</title>
 <link href="http://embrangler.com/tag/resolution/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://embrangler.com/tag/resolution"/>
 <updated>2012-02-28T22:54:09-08:00</updated>
 <id>http://embrangler.com/</id>
 <author>
   <name>Paul Craciunoiu</name>
   <email>paul@craciunoiu.net</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Belated birthday resolutions</title>
   <link href="http://embrangler.com/2012/01/belated-birthday-resolutions"/>
   <updated>2012-01-23T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
   <id>http://embrangler.com/2012/01/belated-birthday-resolutions</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m over a month late on &lt;a href='http://embrangler.com/2010/12/belated-birthday-resolutions/#onward_i_say'&gt;my promise&lt;/a&gt;. But it can still be a tradition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Table of contents:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href='#why'&gt;Why?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href='#thanks_previous_year'&gt;Thanks, previous year!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='#understand_my_place_on_the_web'&gt;Understand my place on the web&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='#take_more_risks'&gt;Take more risks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='#take_more_steps_back_think_ahead'&gt;Take more steps back, think ahead&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='#use_the_power_of_choice'&gt;Use the power of choice&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href='#what_now'&gt;What now?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='#improve_social_life'&gt;Improve social life&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='#eat_less_meat'&gt;Eat less meat&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='#develop_management_leadership_skills'&gt;Develop management/leadership skills&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='#learn_about_emerging_markets_and_ideas'&gt;Learn about emerging markets and ideas&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href='#onward_i_say'&gt;Onward, I say!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id='why'&gt;Why?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s been a new year. And my birthday. In 2011, so much has changed that I could spend weeks just thinking about it, doing nothing else, and still learning from it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I &lt;a href='http://embrangler.com/2010/12/belated-birthday-resolutions/'&gt;wrote a similar post&lt;/a&gt; shortly after my last birthday, and I like the title so I&amp;#8217;m keeping it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='thanks_previous_year'&gt;Thanks, previous year!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking back to the end of 2010, I had set out to fulfill 4 concrete goals:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understand my place on the web&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Take more risks&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Take more steps back, think ahead&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Use the power of choice&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time to grade myself :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='1_understand_my_place_on_the_web'&gt;1. Understand my place on the web.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Grade: D+&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I knew this was a stretch - I am still not sure where I want to be. In 2011, I moved from &lt;a href='http://mozilla.com'&gt;being a web developer at Mozilla&lt;/a&gt; to starting my own company, &lt;a href='http://sowink.com'&gt;SoWink&lt;/a&gt;. I learned that working for a social product is extremely fun. I recently increased my open source contributions to the web as a whole and am planning to continue this trend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But do I really understand where I want to be years from now? Or even this year? No. I&amp;#8217;m considering this goal a moderate success, but mostly &lt;strong&gt;a failure&lt;/strong&gt;. A failure from which I should be learning a lesson. What is that lesson? I&amp;#8217;ll have to think about it&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='2_take_more_risks'&gt;2. Take more risks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Grade: A-&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Definitely achieved. Starting a company, moving, traveling alone, going hang gliding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would have been even better if I had taken more time to learn more about the non-technical essentials of running a company. But that would have taken time from something else, surely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='3_take_more_steps_back_think_ahead'&gt;3. Take more steps back, think ahead&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Grade: B&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve spent some time thinking about my future, life, and what matters. This is worth a separate blog post in itself. I&amp;#8217;m still not satisfied with my time perspective. I want to spend more time thinking about the big picture. I want to have a better grasp of the next few years, and maintain a better balance in my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to thank the people closest to me for asking me thought-provoking questions throughout the year that have encouraged me to do this more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='4_use_the_power_of_choice'&gt;4. Use the power of choice&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Grade: A&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I have still occasionally victimized myself, I understand now that it is difficult not to - especially when under heavy stress. But the past year has taught me to say no more, to negotiate better, to actively choose my path. Most of all, it has taught me that &lt;em&gt;I do&lt;/em&gt; have the power of choice, that &lt;em&gt;I can&lt;/em&gt; do what I want, and that grabbing an opportunity and making the most of it can really change one&amp;#8217;s life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working at a startup, I have had to continually adjust my expectations, evaluate how the product has been going, how much work can really be done, become better at estimating and less worried about missing deadlines. I went through several failures, delayed launches, intense debates and arguments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Failing fast and often has taught me how to deal with stress better. It has the downside of not giving me enough time to think and learn from it, so I&amp;#8217;d like to take some time this month of January to think back more and jot down lessons learned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='what_now'&gt;What now?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since last year went so well, I&amp;#8217;m setting some stretch goals for this year, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='#improve_social_life'&gt;Improve social life&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='#eat_less_meat'&gt;Eat less meat&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='#develop_managementleadership_skills'&gt;Develop management/leadership skills&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='#learn_about_emerging_markets_and_ideas'&gt;Learn about emerging markets and ideas&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id='improve_social_life'&gt;Improve social life&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve been living in the US for a long time now, and I&amp;#8217;ve yet to reach the social life that I want. I&amp;#8217;ve got some of everything, but not enough. My social network is not very responsive nor extremely well aligned with my values and goals. Obviously this is my fault and my responsibility. I want to change that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, this year, I will focus on spending more time with people who I&amp;#8217;ve neglected and deserved better, and also meet some new ones, both for personal and professional reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What am I looking for?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Friends for activities, to exchange personal ideas, and to generally improve each other&amp;#8217;s life through motivation and keeping one in check. Awesome people to hang out with, basically.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Talented mentors, be they engineers, managers, investors, or otherwise people with experience that can help me with advice and whom I can look up to.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ultimate goal:&lt;/strong&gt; fulfilment and satisfaction with where I live and what activities I do, as well as where my life is heading, socially. More concretely, surrounding myself with a network that helps me grow and be generally happier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='eat_less_meat'&gt;Eat less meat&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2011 I met some people who inspired me to eat less meat. I tried it for a while, but ultimately fell back into habit and the convenience of eating meat. This year, I want to try harder, even if I have to go a bit out of my way. Some of the reasons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The industry of meat production and distribution is absolutely disgusting and cruel (both to animals and to workers).&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;It&amp;#8217;s not an efficient means to feed ourselves as a population.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;It&amp;#8217;s very unhealthy, and most of the meat is full of hormones and additives that would not be necessary if proper treatment and procedures were in place.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I won&amp;#8217;t go into details, you can do the research yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ultimate goal:&lt;/strong&gt; eat meat at most once a week. If I can do this for even just 3 months this year, I&amp;#8217;ll be happy. If I think I can go beyond this, I will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='develop_managementleadership_skills'&gt;Develop management/leadership skills&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, I &lt;a href='http://www.crunchbase.com/company/sowink'&gt;founded a company&lt;/a&gt;. I didn&amp;#8217;t even stop to blog about it. Expect a blog post with further details soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the things I learned is that I enjoy helping other people through management and leadership. It would be ideal if I could work in a position that allowed me to be a technical lead of some sort, and be responsible for one or more of:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;technical product decisions&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;scalability, performance, team technical culture (e.g. peer programming, workshops, etc)&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;developer professional growth, helping others learn more and find/understand their career path&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;drive innovation and user experience from a technical side&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ultimate goal:&lt;/strong&gt; strengthen my social and leadership skills, with a technical focus. Qualify for more-social technical-positions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='learn_about_emerging_markets_and_ideas'&gt;Learn about emerging markets and ideas&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being aware of the market and new ideas is important for playing a conscious, proactive role in society. One can do this by keeping up with market trends, new technologies and what technical changes are happening overseas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lumped in with this, I&amp;#8217;d like to learn the basics about the business and legal side of technology, which would help me understand and better communicate with people working in these fields, as well as how to be better at it myself, why not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ultimate goal:&lt;/strong&gt; understand what society is doing as a whole, technologically and economically, and what are the areas of growth and decline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='onward_i_say'&gt;Onward, I say!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;11 months from now, I will report back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to everyone who contributed to my life in 2011!&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Belated birthday resolutions</title>
   <link href="http://embrangler.com/2010/12/belated-birthday-resolutions"/>
   <updated>2010-12-11T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
   <id>http://embrangler.com/2010/12/belated-birthday-resolutions</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Table of contents:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href='#why'&gt;Why?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href='#thanks_previous_year'&gt;Thanks, previous year!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href='#what_now'&gt;What now?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='#understand_my_place_on_the_web'&gt;Understand my place on the web&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='#take_more_risks'&gt;Take more risks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='#take_more_steps_back_think_ahead'&gt;Take more steps back, think ahead&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='#use_the_power_of_choice'&gt;Use the power of choice&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href='#onward_i_say'&gt;Onward, I say!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id='why'&gt;Why?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was my birthday recently. And I&amp;#8217;ve always been a fan of resolutions. I look at them as an opportunity to learn, plan something great, and stick with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, posting them here is an incentive to follow through! By all means, remind me of what promised to achieve next year and make me feel bad if it doesn&amp;#8217;t happen :D&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='thanks_previous_year'&gt;Thanks, previous year!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, I&amp;#8217;ll take the opportunity to look back on my previous year and what has gone well. Be thankful, yada yada.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finished my undergraduate education while working an average of 25 hours per week (last two quarters). Thank you, &lt;a href='http://ucsc.edu'&gt;UC Santa Cruz&lt;/a&gt; for having a good CS program and gathering a bunch of smart engineers too. I am truly grateful of all the opportunities UCSC has offered me.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Learned a &lt;em&gt;ton&lt;/em&gt; about web development, the web in general. I&amp;#8217;m much more confident with the knowledge acquired about my field now. Thank you, Mozilla (mostly webdevs ;) for that. And also thank you, internet!&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Became much more organized and productive. (This is something I look forward to growing even further in the next year.) Thanks to people I&amp;#8217;ve spoken with, a bunch of books I&amp;#8217;ve read and talks I&amp;#8217;ve listened to, as well as one, very interesting seminar at UC Santa Cruz entitled &amp;#8220;Transformative Action&amp;#8221;.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Traveled to a bunch of places (Romania, Hawaii, Puerto Rico, Miami, Yosemite, etc) which motivated me to make &lt;a href='/list/'&gt;a list&lt;/a&gt;. I am thankful to really good friends (one in particular) without whom I would not have done this!&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Slowly but surely came to a decision about going back to school: will wait for at least one more year before applying to graduate schools. Maybe more.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id='what_now'&gt;What now?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this next year, I&amp;#8217;ve decided to keep it simple. Just &lt;strong&gt;4 concrete actions:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='#understand_my_place_on_the_web'&gt;Understand my place on the web&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='#take_more_risks'&gt;Take more risks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='#take_more_steps_back_think_ahead'&gt;Take more steps back, think ahead&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='#use_the_power_of_choice'&gt;Use the power of choice&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id='understand_my_place_on_the_web'&gt;Understand my place on the web&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, I&amp;#8217;ll be honest - this one is a stretch. How about just understanding it better??&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know I want to be on the web. What exactly would my role be? What could &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; do that would make the most difference and at the same time coincide with my values. For this year, I will probably look at this more from a web developer&amp;#8217;s perspective than anything else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ultimate goal:&lt;/strong&gt; more confident about the purpose of my contributions to the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='take_more_risks'&gt;Take more risks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;True - this year has had its risks (jumping from a plane, some crazy hikes, other social or work-related acts that were out of my comfort zone), but by and large, I haven&amp;#8217;t taken chances as much as I know I can. I also want to be more confident in my abilities and this will help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to become more open to risk. Maybe I will try something like &lt;a href='http://sneakylittlefox.tumblr.com/post/2053967413/rejection-therapy-an-introduction'&gt;rejection therapy&lt;/a&gt;. The areas I want to focus on are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;social skillzz - uh, need I say more? computer nerd + social skills = ???&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;webdev work - initiative, initiative, initiative&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;UX - sometimes I don&amp;#8217;t do as good of a job on UI/UX because I stick with the comfy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ultimate goal:&lt;/strong&gt; become much more comfortable with failure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='take_more_steps_back_think_ahead'&gt;Take more steps back, think ahead&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting over-involved in little things can make me forget about what&amp;#8217;s really important. I want to think about the future more and the past less. That&amp;#8217;s what my &lt;a href='http://www.thetimeparadox.com/surveys/ztpi/'&gt;ZTPI&lt;/a&gt; index indicates too ;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Decide on when I will go back to school&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Elaborate on what I see happening for me in the next 2-5 years (I&amp;#8217;ll be happy with 2, but 5 would be an overachievement :)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ultimate goal:&lt;/strong&gt; In the words of Brian Tracy and Philip Zimbardo, I want to &lt;em&gt;expand my time perspective&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='use_the_power_of_choice'&gt;Use the power of choice&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Choice empowers us. Two things here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I want to make an active choice when the opportunity arises - instead of, say, passively deferring.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Say &lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt; more. Much too often I try to be nice and say yes, but time does not permit me to do everything.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ultimate goal:&lt;/strong&gt; become more realistic about how much I can really do, and stop feeling like a victim sometimes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='onward_i_say'&gt;Onward, I say!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;12 months from now, &lt;strong&gt;I will&lt;/strong&gt; report back. Seriously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to everyone who made this year of my life awesome!&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
